so now we will look at one of the
so-called lru approximation algorithms
which this one is called NMU or not most
recently used and it's trying to
approximate the performance of lru but
with less activity on hits so again NMU
stands for not most recently used the
way it would work is that we would track
which one block in the set is the most
recently used one at any given time and
then when we need to replace something
we pick a block that is not the block
that is the most recently used so for
example we can pick randomly among the
other blocks but we save the most
recently used block from eviction from
the cache so how do we track which block
is mru let's say we have an nway set
asstive cache and we want to track the
mru block for each set we need only one
mru pointer per set we only need to know
which block has been the most recently
accessed one in the set so for example
if we have a two-way set asstive cache
we only need one bit to tell us which of
the two is the most recently accessed if
we have a four-way set asstive cache we
will have a 2bit pointer that tells us
which of the four has been the most
recently accessed and so on compare this
to n lru counters that we need per set
in a four-way set assertive cache we
would need need a 2bit pointer for
NMU we would need four 2bit lru counters
to maintain lru so this policy keeps end
times less state for an N wasted asstive
cash than the true lru policy it turns
out that this policy Works reasonably
well it does have a heat rate that is
slightly lower than a true lru but if
this is what it takes to make our cash
go from two cycles hit time to one cycle
hit time it might be worth it a
disadvantage of this policy is that
although it prevents the most recently
accessed line from being evicted it
doesn't know what the order is among the
rest of them so there is a truly least
recently used block among these three
for example but we don't know which one
so we'll pick one of these three and
might select something that is not the
least recently used so although this
works well because the most frequently
accessed thing will be saved in the cash
it is slightly weaker than through lru
because of this because it doesn't know
which one is the really least recently
used so what we might want to have is a
policy that is still simpler than
lru but keeps more track about what's
less recently used than the mru